<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:date="java:java.util.Date"
      xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-3.xsd">
   <titleInfo>
      <title>Members of the School of Microbiology</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name authority="" type="">
      <namePart/>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text" authority="marcrelator">photographer</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">pht</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource collection="yes">still image</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="aat">black-and-white photographs</genre>
   <identifier type="legacy" displayLabel="Prints Number">prints20173</identifier>
   <identifier type="accessionNumber">RG-30/1/10.011</identifier>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm>Charlottesville (Va.)</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateCreated encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">1952-03</dateCreated>
   </originInfo>
   <location>
      <physicalLocation>Historical Collections &amp; Services, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, Charlottesville, Va.</physicalLocation>
   </location>
   <accessCondition type="restrictionOnAccess" displayLabel="Access to the Collection">RESTRICTED</accessCondition>
   <accessCondition type="useAndReproduction" displayLabel="Use and Reproduction">Contact Claude Moore Health Sciences Library for Conditions of Use</accessCondition>
   <abstract>Members of the School of Microbiology, from left to right, Dr. Catherine
                    Russell, Dr. Alto E. Feller, Dr. Wesley Volk, and L. Lee Kupferberg. From the
                    UVa Medical Alumni News Letter, March 1952. The attached article is entitled
                    "Schools Created From Old School of Bacteriology Offer Interesting Examples
                    of New Educational Trends," and reads: "What alumni remember as the
                    School of Bacteriology and Preventative Medicine gas evolved into two separate
                    schools -- the School of Microbiology and the School of Social and Environmental
                    Medicine.... These schools...are representative of the new trends in medical
                    teaching and theory that are developing at the University Department of Medicine
                    as they are at other progressive medical centers throughout the country. "A
                    summary of the program of the School of Microbiology and its Chariman, Dr. Alto
                    E. Feller, could be made in two words -- teaching and research -- but behind
                    these are many theories unused in the school days of most University Medical
                    Alumni. Teaching: The catalogue describes Microbiology as 'A study of
                    host-parasite relationships of medical importance and of the principles of
                    infection and immunity. It is a course which furnishes the student with the
                    fundamentals of microbiology needed for continued study of the mechanisms of
                    infectious disease, for critical appraisal of medical literature and for a
                    rational approach to the problems of diagnosis, treatment and prevention of
                    infectious diseases.' "The course in Microbiology this year, however,
                    offers even more. A study of it demonstrates the integration of pre-clinical and
                    clinical that is takin gplace in the University Department of Medicine. It is
                    trying in t he mechanisms of disease with the basic sciences by bringing
                    clinical, epidemiological and preventive medical aspects into its teaching
                    rather than to confine the study to the fundamental technological picture alone.
                    "Second year men, who in years past had little knowledge of the whole
                    patient, see cases presented that represent infectious diseases such as
                    pneumonia, subacute bacterial endocarditis, tuberculosis, septicemia, etc.
                    Discussions follow as to how the agents produce the disease and how these agents
                    behave in the population. Pre-clinical students report a heightened interest in
                    these presentations. While engrossed in the study of the biochemical,
                    biophysical and biological properties of micro-organisms, they are naturally
                    anxious to see also a little of the type [of] medicine they will know in later
                    years. In addition Dr. Feller presents the basic science picture of microbiology
                    to the third year clinical students when he meets with them one and a half hours
                    each week, and with the house staff attends medical ward rounds. He is also an
                    active participant in weekly clinico-pathological conferences. "Research:
                    "'A vigorous teaching program,' Dr. Feller said, 'can be
                    maintained only by a staff which is also engaged in research. Every member of
                    the School of Microbiology is absorbed in the solution of a special problem. Dr.
                    Catherine Russel, Instructor, is working on 'Leptospira Infections in the
                    Developing Chick Embryo,' which research is supported by a grant from the
                    U.S. Public Health Service. Dr. Wesley A. Volk, Acting Assistant Professor, is
                    engaged in a basic research program on bacterial metabolism. Dr. Feller, with L.
                    Lee Kupferberg, Research Assistant, is recipient of a grant from the Armed
                    Forces Epidemiological Board for wokr in isolating the common cold virus.
                    "This emphasis on research extends to students also. They are encouraged
                    not only to think about research problems, but to come into the laboratories to
                    try a hand. "The long-range plan of the School of Microbiology includes the
                    organization of a program whereby house staff members can rotate through the
                    school and receive training. Looking into the future, Dr. Feller also hopes to
                    establish a graduate student program leading to the Ph.D. Degree."</abstract>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="aat">black-and-white photographs</form>
      <digitalOrigin>reformatted digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>image/tiff</internetMediaType>
      <note displayLabel="Staff Note">Original Negative Present</note>
      <note displayLabel="Copy Negative"/>
   </physicalDescription>
   <note type="admin">Negative included in folder</note>
   <subject authority="tgn">
      <hierarchicalGeographic>
         <country>United States</country>
         <state>Virginia</state>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
      </hierarchicalGeographic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
      <topic>Faculty</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
      <topic>Students</topic>
   </subject>
   <relatedItem type="series" displayLabel="Part of">
      <titleInfo>
         <nonSort>The</nonSort>
         <title>University of Virginia Visual History Collection</title>
      </titleInfo>
   </relatedItem>
   <relatedItem type="series" displayLabel="Appears in">
      <titleInfo>
         <title>UVa Medical Alumni News Letter</title>
      </titleInfo>
      <part>
         <detail type="volume">
            <number>March, 1952</number>
         </detail>
         <detail type="issue">
            <number/>
         </detail>
      </part>
   </relatedItem>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordContentSource authority="marcorg">viu</recordContentSource>
      <recordOrigin>Created programmatically by Digital Curation Services.</recordOrigin>
      <languageOfCataloging>
         <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
      </languageOfCataloging>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2012-08-15T19:06:29.729Z</recordCreationDate>
   </recordInfo>
</mods>