<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:date="java:java.util.Date"
      xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-3.xsd">
   <titleInfo>
      <title>Governor John S. Battle and Advisors Visiting Hospital Wards</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name authority="" type="">
      <namePart/>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text" authority="marcrelator">photographer</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">pht</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource collection="yes">still image</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="aat">black-and-white photographs</genre>
   <identifier type="legacy" displayLabel="Prints Number">prints20157</identifier>
   <identifier type="accessionNumber">RG-30/1/10.011</identifier>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm>Charlottesville (Va.)</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateCreated encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">1953</dateCreated>
   </originInfo>
   <location>
      <physicalLocation>Historical Collections &amp; Services, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, Charlottesville, Va.</physicalLocation>
   </location>
   <accessCondition type="restrictionOnAccess" displayLabel="Access to the Collection">RESTRICTED</accessCondition>
   <accessCondition type="useAndReproduction" displayLabel="Use and Reproduction">Contact Claude Moore Health Sciences Library for Conditions of Use</accessCondition>
   <abstract>This image was on the cover of the October, 1953 issue of the Medical Alumni
                    News Letter, titled "State Budget Time And the Hospital Pleads Again."
                    The relevant article, entitled "The Hospital: Request for State Money And
                    How Can Alumni Help," reads (in part): "For the fourth consecutive
                    meeting of the Virginia General Assembly in a period of eight years, officials
                    and alumni of the University's Medical Center will plead with the State to
                    pull the University Hospital out of its fire-hazardous, inefficient,
                    money-consuming conidtion and make of it a center that can handle properly its
                    expanded patient load and its medical educational role in the State. President
                    Darden, fearful of a catastrophic fire that could wipe out everything and
                    concerned with the high cost of maintaining antiquated hospital buildings which
                    year after year frustrates plans for educational development in other deserving
                    departments of the University, is wholeheartedly leading the request for State
                    appropriations. Aiding the University's President, deans and alumni, will
                    be a number of prominent non-alumni doctors, Virginia businessmen and lawyers
                    from every section of the State who recognize that the request of the University
                    Hospital is not a local project of a 'pork barrel' nature...but an
                    essential need affecting every person in the State who might be referred to the
                    Hospital for treatment of a difficult problem which could not be handled in his
                    home town.... Formal request that the appropriation be made a part of the
                    Governor's Budget was put to Governor Battle and members of his Advisory
                    Budget Commission when they visited the Hospital on September twenty-fifth. The
                    group of friends of the Hospital, assisting Medical Alumni President V. W.
                    Archer, Dean T. H. Hunter, Assistant Dean H. B. Mulholland and Hospital Director
                    John M. Stacey in presenting the need, made what many believe to be the
                    strongest appeal ever to come from the Hospital-Medical School. Describing the
                    Hospital's three main functions...as a laboratory for medical students in
                    the clinical years; as a reference center for difficult cases from every section
                    of the State; and as a general hospital to provide care for the indigent in the
                    local area...members of the group urged the budget planners to understand that
                    the appropriation is 'essential to the growth, essential to the very
                    continuation of the medical school.' 'Physical faculties are not only
                    inadequate, but at best the whole situation is unfair to the people of
                    Virginia' who rely on the University as a medical center, said Mr. [P.]
                    Hazelgrove [Staunton lawyer]. Unless improvements are made the school will lose
                    its 'great collection of medical talent, its prestige and reputation.'
                    Others brought out that though the pre-clinical laboratories are equipped to
                    handle an increased number of students, the hospital facilities prevent
                    additions for the clinical years of study and prevent development of
                    postgraduate teacing of Virginia doctors who wish to come to the clinics to
                    study. Dr. [Alex F.] Roberston [of Staunton] stressed that the hospital
                    equipment was in 'deplorable' condition -- worse than any State
                    medical school he knew of. Fire hazards amount to 'a terrible condition we
                    shouldn't allow to exist,' said Mr. [J. B.] Woodward [President of the
                    Newport News Shipbuilding and Drydock Company in Newport News], pointing out
                    that such conditions wouldn't be tolerated in a business firm. 'With
                    all these helpless people, a fire here would cause a real tragedy.' Justice
                    [C. Vernon] Spratley [of the Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals, of Hampton],
                    emphasizing the seriousness of conditions, said a 'real sense of duty'
                    led him to journey from Hampton to Charlottesville to add his voice to appeals
                    for the Hosptial appropriation. It is highly important to correct conditions in
                    the overcrowded Negro wards -- or else critics of segregation would raise the
                    cry of discrimination -- Mr. Darden answered Governor Battle's questions
                    about the Negro facilities. 'We are doing the best we can for our Negro
                    patients under circumstances that are almost intolerable,' Mr. Darden said.
                    'They receive the best treatment, equal to that given any other patient,
                    but the physical conditions in Negro Wards are fearfully poor. 'The State
                    deserves to do better for them, and the Negro people deserve better from those
                    controlling the State's political destinies...We are not doing what in good
                    conscience ought to be done.' ....Backing up their words with a 'see
                    for yourself' tour, officials and friends of the University escorted the
                    budget planners through the 50-year old wings of the Hospital. They pointed out
                    evidence of delapidation, danger and inefficiency...the overcrowded wards where
                    some patients have to be bedded in narrow, dark corridors...nursing stations
                    crowded into halls along with storage of clean and soiled laundry...high cost of
                    housekeeping intensified by problems of rodent and insect control, cleaning of
                    exposed pipes...overloaded electrical installations...inadequate number of fire
                    exits...food serving stations which have been crowded into halls where
                    employees, patients and visitors pass continually...limited isolation areas for
                    nursery and obstetrical suites...health hazards risked because surgical suite is
                    bisected by main public corridors and tuberculosis patients are often cared for
                    on open wards...overcrowding of out-patient department which was designed for 90
                    patients per day and now handles as many as 325...lack of central location for
                    ancillary services...high c ost of transporting patients to X-ray...danger to
                    patients caused by long distances that must be traveled from service to
                    service...dangers presented by obsolete elevators...high cost of transporting
                    food, laundry and supplies from loading stations to wards...high cost of
                    maintenace of old buildings which have settled, casuing plaster on walls to
                    break and fall, masonry to continually come loose, roof to need constant
                    repairs, floors to break...inflexibility of wards to care for an expanded
                    patient load which has increased from 65,441 days care in 1933 to 143,210 in
                    1952.... The first of three tours of the Hospital for members of the Virginia
                    General Assembly was held October eighth. Other tours will follow on October
                    twenty-second and November nineteenth in accordance with a plan which requires
                    assemblymen to visit all State institutions."</abstract>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="aat">black-and-white photographs</form>
      <digitalOrigin>reformatted digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>image/tiff</internetMediaType>
      <note displayLabel="Staff Note">Original Negative Present</note>
      <note displayLabel="Copy Negative"/>
   </physicalDescription>
   <note type="admin">Photo used in the UVa Health Sciences Library Exhibit - African Americans in
                    the Health Care Profession</note>
   <subject authority="tgn">
      <hierarchicalGeographic>
         <country>United States</country>
         <state>Virginia</state>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
      </hierarchicalGeographic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
   </subject>
   <relatedItem type="series" displayLabel="Part of">
      <titleInfo>
         <nonSort>The</nonSort>
         <title>University of Virginia Visual History Collection</title>
      </titleInfo>
   </relatedItem>
   <relatedItem type="series" displayLabel="Appears in">
      <titleInfo>
         <title>Uva Medical Alumni News Letter</title>
      </titleInfo>
      <part>
         <detail type="volume">
            <number>October, 1953</number>
         </detail>
         <detail type="issue">
            <number/>
         </detail>
      </part>
   </relatedItem>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordContentSource authority="marcorg">viu</recordContentSource>
      <recordOrigin>Created programmatically by Digital Curation Services.</recordOrigin>
      <languageOfCataloging>
         <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
      </languageOfCataloging>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2012-08-15T19:06:29.716Z</recordCreationDate>
   </recordInfo>
</mods>