<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:date="java:java.util.Date"
      xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-3.xsd">
   <titleInfo>
      <title>Piedmont Sanatorium (Burkeville, VA)</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name authority="" type="">
      <namePart/>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text" authority="marcrelator">photographer</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">pht</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource collection="yes">still image</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="aat">black-and-white photographs</genre>
   <identifier type="legacy" displayLabel="Prints Number">prints20167</identifier>
   <identifier type="accessionNumber">RG-30/1/10.011</identifier>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm>Charlottesville (Va.)</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateCreated encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">1918</dateCreated>
   </originInfo>
   <location>
      <physicalLocation>Historical Collections &amp; Services, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, Charlottesville, Va.</physicalLocation>
   </location>
   <accessCondition type="restrictionOnAccess" displayLabel="Access to the Collection">RESTRICTED</accessCondition>
   <accessCondition type="useAndReproduction" displayLabel="Use and Reproduction">Contact Claude Moore Health Sciences Library for Conditions of Use</accessCondition>
   <abstract>From the Virginia Department of Health Health Bulletin, Piedmont Sanatorium
                    Number, Vol. II, No. 1, November, 1938: "....Prior to 1918 no adequate
                    public facilities existed in Virginia for the treatment of the tuberculous
                    Negro. Several years previous to that time a campaign was conducted by the State
                    Department of Health to remedy this situation. In these efforts the Virginia
                    Tuberculosis Society and the Negro Organization Society actively and inspiringly
                    cooperated. It was appreciated then, as it is today, that tuberculosis among the
                    colored race would have to be reduced if satisfactory progress in lowering both
                    the incidence and death rates in the general population were to be achieved.
                    "In 1916 the Legislature made an appropriation to purchase land and erect a
                    small hospital for the institutional treatment of Negroes suffering with
                    tuberculosis. Population and transportation factors were responsible in locating
                    the sanatorium one mile east of Burkeville. "The work of clearing the land
                    and remodling the farm structures, already on the 310 acre tract, was started in
                    the latter part of 1916. Actual construction on the new buildings began in 1917.
                    One twenty-five bed pavilion and the administration quarters were completed in
                    March, 1918. On April 22nd of that year Piedmont Sanatorium formally was opened
                    and the first patient admitted. "With Dr. H. C. Carter as superintendent
                    and Miss Mary E. Gilliam as head nurse representing the professional staff,
                    assisted by twelve employees, this institution, the first of its kind in the
                    South, immediately began to make history. The twenty-five beds soon were filled.
                    A waiting list at once developed which, incidentally, has existed from that time
                    to the present. "In June of 1918 the State Tuberculosis Association offered
                    $5,000 for a second pavilion provided by the State Board of Health would
                    complete it. As a result of the Moton Building was erected. With a rearrangement
                    of facilities in the Agnes Randolph Pavilion and this new construction the total
                    bed capacity in September, 1918, was increased to 70. "In September of 1918
                    a course of study for nurses was outlined by the staff. The orginal class with
                    an enrollment of two students began work shortly thereafter, marking the start
                    of the Piedmont Sanatorium Trainig School for Colored Women. It is significant
                    that this was the first school in the United States training Negro women in
                    tuberculosis nursing. Since 1925 a six-months, post-graduate course has been
                    made available. Since 1918 seventy-four nurses have been graduated. Many of
                    these alumni now are supervisors of Virginia sanatoria and of others in southern
                    States; several are engaged in Public Health and social service work, while
                    others are doing private duty in a New York City tuberculosis hospital. The
                    importance of this branch of training is becoming more evident each year.
                    "During 191 occupational therapy was introduced, made possible through a
                    donation from the National Tuberculosis Association. This work has continued
                    ever since that time. All patients going to meals and on exercise attend the
                    classes. "Again, with the financial aid of the National Tuberculosis
                    Association a course of instruction, including clinical work, was offered to the
                    colored physicians of Virginia; it was well attended and highly successful.
                    "Addtions to the professional and maintenance staffs, while slow and few,
                    were made in a successful effort to keep pace with the institution's ever
                    increasing needs. Essential equipment from time to time also was added. "In
                    May, 1921, a small nurses' home was completed; and in 1923 the first half
                    of a new building for bed cases, provided for by the General Assembly in 1922,
                    received its first patients. The completion of this wing increased the patient
                    capacity to 98. "The spiritual and moral welfare of the institution's
                    patients and employees was not forgotten. Early in 1922 the Piedmont Sanatorium
                    Welfare Board was organized. In May, 1923, the Board requested permission to
                    erect a chapel. By the combined efforts of the members of this Board, the
                    patients, staff, employees, and many friends $3,000 was collected. The chapel
                    was dedicated in April, 1924. "The second wing to the infirmary was opened
                    for patients in March, 1926. It was named 'The Carter Building.' The
                    capacity thus was increased to 150. The Negro Organization Society donated funds
                    for equipment of the basement of this building for friends and relatives of the
                    patients, also for colored physicians, who visit the institution. "On March
                    1, 1931, Dr. J. B. Woodson was appointed superintendent and medical director,
                    Dr. Carter having previously died. During the seven years of Dr. Woodson's
                    administration many improvements to the grounds and buildings have been made.
                    "To date nearly 5,500 patients have been treated, exclusive of the large
                    number of patients referred by the physicians to the institution for
                    examination. "Twenty years have passed since the sanatorium was
                    established. The staff now consists of the superintendent and medical director,
                    assistant medical director, assistant physician, superintendent of nurses,
                    dietitian-housekeeper, technician, business executive, and medical department
                    secretary." Cf. prints20166.</abstract>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="aat">black-and-white photographs</form>
      <digitalOrigin>reformatted digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>image/tiff</internetMediaType>
      <note displayLabel="Staff Note">Original Negative Present</note>
      <note displayLabel="Copy Negative"/>
   </physicalDescription>
   <note type="admin">Negative included in folder, Photo used in the UVa Health Sciences Library
                    Exhibit - African Americans in the Health Care Profession. Cf.
                    prints20166.</note>
   <subject authority="tgn">
      <hierarchicalGeographic>
         <country>United States</country>
         <state>Virginia</state>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
      </hierarchicalGeographic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
      <topic>Health System</topic>
   </subject>
   <relatedItem type="series" displayLabel="Part of">
      <titleInfo>
         <nonSort>The</nonSort>
         <title>University of Virginia Visual History Collection</title>
      </titleInfo>
   </relatedItem>
   <relatedItem type="series" displayLabel="Appears in">
      <titleInfo>
         <title/>
      </titleInfo>
      <part>
         <detail type="volume">
            <number/>
         </detail>
         <detail type="issue">
            <number/>
         </detail>
      </part>
   </relatedItem>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordContentSource authority="marcorg">viu</recordContentSource>
      <recordOrigin>Created programmatically by Digital Curation Services.</recordOrigin>
      <languageOfCataloging>
         <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
      </languageOfCataloging>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2012-08-15T19:06:29.725Z</recordCreationDate>
   </recordInfo>
</mods>