<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:date="java:java.util.Date"
      xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-3.xsd">
   <titleInfo>
      <title>Infirmary Building - Piedmont Sanatorium (Burkeville, VA)</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name authority="" type="">
      <namePart/>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text" authority="marcrelator">photographer</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">pht</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource collection="yes">still image</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="aat">black-and-white negatives</genre>
   <identifier type="legacy" displayLabel="Prints Number">prints20166</identifier>
   <identifier type="accessionNumber">RG-30/1/10.011</identifier>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm>Charlottesville (Va.)</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateCreated encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">1918</dateCreated>
   </originInfo>
   <location>
      <physicalLocation>Historical Collections &amp; Services, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, Charlottesville, Va.</physicalLocation>
   </location>
   <accessCondition type="restrictionOnAccess" displayLabel="Access to the Collection">RESTRICTED</accessCondition>
   <accessCondition type="useAndReproduction" displayLabel="Use and Reproduction">Contact Claude Moore Health Sciences Library for Conditions of Use</accessCondition>
   <abstract>"Though less encumbered by the sentiments of the antebellum South
                    (expressed by a prominent Richmond physician in 1850 when he observed that
                    'the African consititution sinks before the heavy blows of the 'heroic
                    school'), the medical profession nonetheless provided separate facilities
                    and personnel for the treatment of black Virginians during the first half of the
                    twentieth century. Physicians and nurses, alarmed by such pressing health
                    concerns as the rise of tuberculosis across the Old Dominion, developed
                    screening and treatment programs tailored to the legal strictures of
                    segregation. Piedmont Sanatorium, founded with state support in 1919, embodied
                    their best efforts providing affordable patient care as well as training for the
                    growing numbers of black professionals in the health services." -- from the
                    UVa Health Sciences Library Exhibit - African Americans in the Health Care
                    Profession. A letter dated Feb. 11, 1919, about the Piedmont Sanitorium from the
                    Commonwealth of Virginia's State Board of Health, addressed to doctors,
                    reads: "Dear Doctor: Piedmont Sanitorium, the State Institution for the
                    treatment of tuberculosis among the colored people of Virginia, was opened April
                    22, 1918, with a capacity for eighty patients. The Sanatorium is one mile east
                    of Burkeville, a junction of the Norfolk &amp; Western and Southern Railroads,
                    and is easily accessible to all parts of the state. The charges are $2.50 per
                    week, or $10.00 per month, payable after four weeks in advance. This rate
                    includes board, medical attention and laundry. The main aim of the Sanatorium is
                    to treat as many people as possible, so that they may return to their homes and
                    educate those with whom they come in contact as to the safegaurds against
                    tuberculosis and the method of curing the disease. To this end, preference in
                    choosing cases for treatment at the sanatorium would naturally go to people in
                    the early stages of the disease. Several advanced cases returned to their homes
                    unimproved or dead will make it impossible for the institution to have a
                    treatable case sent on. We need one or more early cases from your locality in
                    order to give the people there concrete evidence in our argument that
                    tuberculosis can be cured. For application blanks and further information, write
                    to Dr. H. G. Carter, Supt., Piedmont Sanatorium, Burkeville, Va. Very truly
                    yours, [Emerson G.] Williams." From a Release by the Hampton Institute
                    Press Service: "Virginia Cares for Colored Consumptives.... Richmond, VA.,
                    Mar. [1919?] -- Miss Agnes D. Randolph, Executive Secretary of the Virginia
                    Anti-Tuberculosis Association, 1110 Capitol Street, makes the following
                    announcement concerning the care of colored consumptive at the Piedmont
                    Sanatorium, which was opened in April, 1918, for the proper care of suffering
                    colored men and women of the Old Dominion. Miss Randolph says: 'The State
                    opened its first hospital for colored patients suffering from tuberculosis or
                    consumption, with forty beds, and, within four months, has added forty more.
                    'There are vacant beds at the hospital today, although there are thousands
                    of patients whose health might be restored by proper treatment. This means that
                    the old false ideas about tuberculosis still hold. 'There are two reasons
                    why there should never be a vacant bed in the hospital at Piedmont so long as
                    there is a consumptive without hospital experience in his own home in Virginia:
                    first, tuberculosis is curable; second, tuberculosis is preventable.
                    'Tuberculosis is curable.... 'For hundreds of years people believed
                    that tuberculosis was incurable; that is, if you had it, you must die.
                    'Fifty years ago, a doctor named Trudeau had the disease and went into the
                    mountains of New York expecting to die. He lived quietly, most of the time out
                    of doors, and, to his surprise, improved. In two or three years one of his
                    friends sent him a consumptive to treat and he also improved. More and more
                    people came. In this way was started in America the treatment of tuberculosis
                    which cures the disease. Hundreds of hospitals have been built since that time
                    and tens of thousands of sick people have been treated and sent back to work.
                    Dr. Trudea and the doctors working since his time have found that the way to
                    treat tuberculosis is by providing rest, fresh air, and good food. 'This
                    sounds easy, but, if you try it at hom, just as soon as you begin to feel better
                    you want to get up and go visiting, or do a little work, and you undo all of the
                    good you had done. In a hospital a doctor and nurse see that you rest and take
                    the cure.' The charge at the Piedmont Sanatorium is $2.50 a week, or $10.00
                    a month. Miss Agnes D. Randolph, 1110 Capitol Street, Richmond, or Dr. H. G.
                    Carter, Burkeville, Va., will gladly furnish additional information." From
                    a letter to Dr. D. B. Cole, Richmond, Va., dated January 6, 1920: 'Dear Dr.
                    Cole: 'The National Association appropriated to Peidmont Sanatorium from
                    March 1, 1919 to March 1, 1920 the sum of $2,500 to establish occupational
                    therapy. A part of this sum was also to be expended for a post-graduate course
                    for the colored doctors of the State. This work, although started late, is
                    fairly well under progress, but has not progressed to the point that we can ask
                    t he Legislature of 1920 to continue same. We ask that the National Association
                    continue this fund during 1920 and 1921, especially in regard to the post
                    graduate work for colored doctors. Untold good can be done in developing this
                    line of work. There are in the State about eighty colored physicians,
                    practically 50% of whom could be persuaded to take a short post-graduate course
                    at Peidmont. 'This work will be discontinued March 1, 1920 unless supported
                    by the National Association, certainly until 1921, and it is our urgent request
                    that you bring this matter to the attention of the National Association at an
                    appropriate time. 'Yours truly, H. G. Carter, Superintendent.' Cf.
                    prints 20167.</abstract>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="aat">black-and-white negatives</form>
      <digitalOrigin>reformatted digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>image/tiff</internetMediaType>
      <note displayLabel="Staff Note">Original Negative Present</note>
      <note displayLabel="Copy Negative"/>
   </physicalDescription>
   <note type="admin">Prints folder contains: Hampton Institue Press Services Release "Virginia
                    Cares for Colored Consumptive"; Letter regarding the opening of Piedmont
                    Sanatorium to doctors; Copy of application for admission to the sanatorium; Copy
                    of invitation from the graduating class of the Piedmont Sanatorium Training
                    School for Nurses (1951); Copy of the VA Dept. of Health - Health Bulletin Vol.
                    III, No.1 (November 1938); Copy of letter from HG. Carter to D.B. Cole regarding
                    a $2500 appropriation to the Sanatorium for occupational therapy; Photo used in
                    the UVa Health Sciences Library Exhibit - African Americans in the Health Care
                    Profession. Cf. prints 20167.</note>
   <subject authority="tgn">
      <hierarchicalGeographic>
         <country>United States</country>
         <state>Virginia</state>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
      </hierarchicalGeographic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
      <topic>Health System</topic>
   </subject>
   <relatedItem type="series" displayLabel="Part of">
      <titleInfo>
         <nonSort>The</nonSort>
         <title>University of Virginia Visual History Collection</title>
      </titleInfo>
   </relatedItem>
   <relatedItem type="series" displayLabel="Appears in">
      <titleInfo>
         <title/>
      </titleInfo>
      <part>
         <detail type="volume">
            <number/>
         </detail>
         <detail type="issue">
            <number/>
         </detail>
      </part>
   </relatedItem>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordContentSource authority="marcorg">viu</recordContentSource>
      <recordOrigin>Created programmatically by Digital Curation Services.</recordOrigin>
      <languageOfCataloging>
         <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
      </languageOfCataloging>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2012-08-15T19:06:29.724Z</recordCreationDate>
   </recordInfo>
</mods>