<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:date="java:java.util.Date"
      xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-3.xsd">
   <titleInfo>
      <title>Portrait of Dr. [James Alexander] Waddell Presented to University</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name authority="" type="">
      <namePart/>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text" authority="marcrelator">photographer</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">pht</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource collection="yes">still image</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="aat">black-and-white photographs</genre>
   <identifier type="legacy" displayLabel="Prints Number">prints20158</identifier>
   <identifier type="accessionNumber">RG-30/1/10.011</identifier>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm>Charlottesville (Va.)</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateCreated encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">1960-06</dateCreated>
   </originInfo>
   <location>
      <physicalLocation>Historical Collections &amp; Services, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, Charlottesville, Va.</physicalLocation>
   </location>
   <accessCondition type="restrictionOnAccess" displayLabel="Access to the Collection">RESTRICTED</accessCondition>
   <accessCondition type="useAndReproduction" displayLabel="Use and Reproduction">Contact Claude Moore Health Sciences Library for Conditions of Use</accessCondition>
   <abstract>Left to right: Dr. W. W. Waddell, Jr., Mrs. W. W. Waddell, Jr., Mrs. Frederick
                    V. Vance, Jr. , Dr. Frederick V. Vance, Jr., Mrs. W. W. Waddell, III, and W. W.
                    Waddell, III. From the Medical Alumni News Letter, May-June 1959: "Dr. W.
                    W. Waddell, Jr., '18, member of the medical faculty at the University of
                    Virginia for the past thirty-six years, and Professor and Chairman of Pediatrics
                    since 1944, was honored with a cocktail party and testimonial dinner at
                    Farmington Country Club on June 9, given by his former residents. Dr.
                    Waddell's resignation as Chairman of the Department of Pediatrics,
                    effective July 1, is in accordance with University policy which requires
                    retirement from adminstrative positions at the age of sixty-five. Dr. Waddell is
                    continuing his pediatric practice and teaching duties as Professor of
                    Pediatrics. Dr. McLemore Birdsong, '37, Professor of Pediatrics, who has
                    been a member of the pediatric faculty under Dr. Wadell for nineteen years, has
                    been named Acting Chairman. A portrait of Dr. Waddell, painted by Bronislaw A.
                    Malieski, was presented to the University of Virginia School of Medicine by Dr.
                    F. Read Hopkins, '26, of Lynchburg, Va., oldest of the residents returning
                    for the present ceremony. Funds for the portrait were contributed by residents
                    who received their pediatric training under Dr. Waddell. Dr. Waddell's
                    daughter, Mrs. Frederick V. Vance, Jr. of Bristol, Tenn., unveiled the portrait,
                    which was accepted on behalf of the medical school by Dr. Thomas H. Hunter,
                    Dean. Dr. Birdsong introduced Dr. Hopkins and served as master of ceremonies. In
                    making the presentation, Dr. Hopkins said: 'It is a privilege to be here on
                    this occasion to say a few words on behalf of the former pediatric residents in
                    honor of our friend -- Dr. Bill Waddell. He is a great clinician, a great
                    teacher, and a great gentleman of the Old Virginia type. 'We have all
                    profited by our close association with him....As h e retires as Chairman of the
                    Department of Pediatrics, we wish him many more happy and useful years, and as a
                    token of our appreciation, we present this portrait to the University.' Dr.
                    Waddell received his M.D. degree from the University of Virginia School of
                    Medicine in 1918; served his internship at Episcopal Hospital in Philadelphia,
                    Pa.; took his residency training in pediatrics at Bellevue Hospital in New York
                    City; and then returned to Virginia as an Instructor in Pediatrics. He became
                    Assistant Professor of Pediatrics in 1927, was promoted to Associate Professor
                    in 1936, and to Professor of Pediatrics in 1944. Dr. Waddell is a member of the
                    American Medical Association, American Academy of Pediatrics, Medical Society of
                    Virginia, Virginia Pediatric Society, and Albemarle County Medical Society. He
                    is author and co-author of numerous articles pertaining to diseases of children.
                    He recorded the first instance of the use of vitamin K in the treatment of
                    hemorrhagic disease of the newborn, and subsequently published numerous articles
                    contributing to the present knowledge concerning the cause, prevention, and
                    treatment of hemorrhagic disease of the newborn." </abstract>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="aat">black-and-white photographs</form>
      <digitalOrigin>reformatted digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>image/tiff</internetMediaType>
      <note displayLabel="Staff Note">Original Negative Present</note>
      <note displayLabel="Copy Negative"/>
   </physicalDescription>
   <note type="admin">Negative included in folder, Article from the Medical Alumni News Letter (pg.
                    5) included in folder</note>
   <subject authority="tgn">
      <hierarchicalGeographic>
         <country>United States</country>
         <state>Virginia</state>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
      </hierarchicalGeographic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
      <topic>Faculty</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
      <topic>Students</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
      <topic>Health System</topic>
   </subject>
   <relatedItem type="series" displayLabel="Part of">
      <titleInfo>
         <nonSort>The</nonSort>
         <title>University of Virginia Visual History Collection</title>
      </titleInfo>
   </relatedItem>
   <relatedItem type="series" displayLabel="Appears in">
      <titleInfo>
         <title>UVa Medi cal Alumni News Letter</title>
      </titleInfo>
      <part>
         <detail type="volume">
            <number>May-June 1960</number>
         </detail>
         <detail type="issue">
            <number/>
         </detail>
      </part>
   </relatedItem>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordContentSource authority="marcorg">viu</recordContentSource>
      <recordOrigin>Created programmatically by Digital Curation Services.</recordOrigin>
      <languageOfCataloging>
         <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
      </languageOfCataloging>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2012-08-15T19:06:29.717Z</recordCreationDate>
   </recordInfo>
</mods>