<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:date="java:java.util.Date"
      xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-3.xsd">
   <titleInfo>
      <title>Dr. William Parson (left), Dr. Po-Young Lee (center), and Dr. Oscar A. Thorup,
                    Jr. (right)</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name authority="" type="">
      <namePart/>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text" authority="marcrelator">photographer</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">pht</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource collection="yes">still image</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="aat">black-and-white photographs</genre>
   <identifier type="legacy" displayLabel="Prints Number">prints20149</identifier>
   <identifier type="accessionNumber">RG-30/1/10.011</identifier>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm>Charlottesville (Va.)</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateCreated encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">1954-10</dateCreated>
   </originInfo>
   <location>
      <physicalLocation>Historical Collections &amp; Services, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, Charlottesville, Va.</physicalLocation>
   </location>
   <accessCondition type="restrictionOnAccess" displayLabel="Access to the Collection">RESTRICTED</accessCondition>
   <accessCondition type="useAndReproduction" displayLabel="Use and Reproduction">Contact Claude Moore Health Sciences Library for Conditions of Use</accessCondition>
   <abstract> This image accompanied an article in the UVa Medical Alumni News Letter,
                    October 1954. The caption under the image reads: "Dr. Po-Young Lee (center)
                    confers with Dr. William Parson (left), Chairman of the Department of Internal
                    Medicine, and Dr. Oscar A. Thorup, Jr., Assistant to the Dean and Instructor in
                    Internal Medicine. Dr. Lee, Chairman of the Department of Medicine of the
                    Severance Union Medical College, Seoul, Korea, began a two-year study program
                    here in September." The accompanying article is entitled "Korean
                    Medical College Chairman Here for Postgraduate Study." The article reads:
                    "Dr. Po-Young Lee, Chairman of the Department of Medicine, Servance Union
                    Medical College, Seoul, Korea, arrived in Charlottesville on September 17 to
                    begin two years of postgraduate study at the University of Virginia School of
                    Medicine. Arrangements for Dr. Lee's two-year program were made by Dr.
                    Myung Sun Kim, President of the Serverance Union Medical College, who visited
                    here in 1951, through correspondence with Dr. William Parson, Chairman of the
                    Department of Internal Medicine and Dr. Thomas H. Hunter, Dean of the School of
                    Medicine and Professor of Internal Medicine. Most of Dr. Lee's expenses are
                    being paid by the mission board of a group of U.S. and Canadian protestant
                    churches, with the University allowing him board and room in the house staff
                    quarters of the University of Virginia Hospital. According to Dr. Kim, there is
                    an urgent need for better medical education in Korea, and the purpose of Dr.
                    Lee's study here is to learn as much as possible about new developments in
                    medicine so that he can return to Korea and pass this knowledge on to other
                    Korean physicians and medical students. Severely damaged during the Korean war,
                    the Severance Union Medical College and its associated hospital were only
                    recently reopened. Facilities for clinical study are still inadequate. While
                    here Dr. Lee will take part in teaching and clinical procedures, and will audit
                    basic science courses in the medical school, as well as the clinical courses. In
                    addition he will be given such clinical responsibility as seems indicated.
                    Wartime conditions, poor food, and poor sanitation have left Koreans in
                    'bad shape,' Dr. Lee says. He estimates that there are at least one
                    million active cases of pulmonary tuberculosis in Korea, with only 400 beds in
                    which to treat them. Peptic ulcers and other gastro-intestinal ailments are also
                    common, he asserts, and he hopes to learn more in this field during his study
                    here. Born in 1910, Dr. Lee received his M.D. degree from Severance Union
                    Medical College in 1937, and a Doctor of Medical Science degree from the Kyoto
                    University Medical School in Japan in 1946. Following internship and graduate
                    study in physiology and medicine, he was appointed to the faculty of the
                    Severance Union Medical College. When the medical college and hospital at Seoul
                    were bombed out during the war, Dr Lee escaped capture by fleeing southward with
                    the army and acting as a civilion [sic] medical officer during the heavy
                    fighting. Married and the father of three children, Dr. Lee accepts the long
                    separation from his family with stoicism. The rehabilitation of Korea cannot be
                    accomplished 'only by the materials,' he says. Highly trained leaders
                    in every field, especially in the field of medicine, are urgently required --
                    and he is grateful for the opportunity to add to his medical knowledge, so that
                    he can go back to Korea and 'train young doctors properly.'" This
                    picture is reprinted, along with an appreciation of Dr. Parsons (d. 2002), in
                    Link, December 2002.</abstract>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="aat">black-and-white photographs</form>
      <digitalOrigin>reformatted digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>image/tiff</internetMediaType>
      <note displayLabel="Staff Note">Original Negative Present</note>
      <note displayLabel="Copy Negative"/>
   </physicalDescription>
   <note type="admin">This picture is reprinted, along with an appreciation of Dr. Parsons (d.
                    2002), in Link, December 2002.</note>
   <subject authority="tgn">
      <hierarchicalGeographic>
         <country>United States</country>
         <state>Virginia</state>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
      </hierarchicalGeographic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
      <topic>Faculty</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
      <topic>Students</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia. School of Nursing</namePart>
      </name>
   </subject>
   <relatedItem type="series" displayLabel="Part of">
      <titleInfo>
         <nonSort>The</nonSort>
         <title>University of Virginia Visual History Collection</title>
      </titleInfo>
   </relatedItem>
   <relatedItem type="series" displayLabel="Appears in">
      <titleInfo>
         <title>UVa Medical Alumni News Letter</title>
      </titleInfo>
      <part>
         <detail type="volume">
            <number>October 1954</number>
         </detail>
         <detail type="issue">
            <number/>
         </detail>
      </part>
   </relatedItem>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordContentSource authority="marcorg">viu</recordContentSource>
      <recordOrigin>Created programmatically by Digital Curation Services.</recordOrigin>
      <languageOfCataloging>
         <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
      </languageOfCataloging>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2012-08-15T19:06:29.709Z</recordCreationDate>
   </recordInfo>
</mods>