<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:date="java:java.util.Date"
      xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-3.xsd">
   <titleInfo>
      <title>Pathology "Round Table"</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <name authority="" type="">
      <namePart/>
      <role>
         <roleTerm type="text" authority="marcrelator">photographer</roleTerm>
         <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">pht</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <typeOfResource collection="yes">still image</typeOfResource>
   <genre authority="aat">black-and-white photographs</genre>
   <identifier type="legacy" displayLabel="Prints Number">prints20175</identifier>
   <identifier type="accessionNumber">RG-30/1/10.011</identifier>
   <originInfo>
      <place>
         <placeTerm>Charlottesville (Va.)</placeTerm>
      </place>
      <dateCreated encoding="w3cdtf" keyDate="yes">1958-07 - 1958-08</dateCreated>
   </originInfo>
   <location>
      <physicalLocation>Historical Collections &amp; Services, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, Charlottesville, Va.</physicalLocation>
   </location>
   <accessCondition type="restrictionOnAccess" displayLabel="Access to the Collection">RESTRICTED</accessCondition>
   <accessCondition type="useAndReproduction" displayLabel="Use and Reproduction">Contact Claude Moore Health Sciences Library for Conditions of Use</accessCondition>
   <abstract>Dr. David E. Smith, Chairman of the Department of Pathology, and some of the
                    members of his staff at the pathology "round table." (Left to right)
                    Dr. Smith, Dr. M. Shannon Allen, Jr., Dr. Yin-Tang Hsu, Dr. C. Richard
                    Chamberlain, Jr., Dr. Frederick Davis, Jr., and Dr. Cornelia Hoch-Ligeti, From
                    the Medical Alumni News Letter, July-August 1958 article "Dr. D. E. Smith
                    Named Chairman Department of Pathology...": "Dr. David E. Smtih was
                    appointed Chairman of the Department of Pathology, effective July 1 [1958],
                    succeeding Dr. James R. Cash. "Dr. Smith has been a Professor at the
                    University since August 1, 1958.... "Since coming to the University, Dr.
                    Smith has concentrated his efforts on the participation of the Department of
                    Pathology in various interdepartmental conferences and graduate teaching
                    programs. He has been responsible for the pathological discussions in the weely
                    [sic] clinico-pathological programs. He has also been interested in intensifying
                    the training program in pathologic anatomy, both for residents on that service
                    and for residents who rotate from the various surgical specialities. "With
                    the aid of various members of the department, particularly Edward G. Stuart, an
                    effort has been made this year to revise some of the features of the teaching
                    program of the second-year course in pathology. The case-teaching method which
                    has been an outstanding feature of that course under Dr. Cash has been
                    continued, but the class slide collection has been revised and enlarged and a
                    series of student seminars has been introduced as a laboratory exercise. With
                    the co-operation of Dr. Alto E. Feller, Chairman of the Department of
                    Microbiology, and Dr. William S. Jordan, Jr., Chairman of the Department of
                    Preventive Medicine, an effort has been made to co-ordinate the students'
                    study of certain topics common to these three courses.... Dr. Smith was born
                    June 9, 1920 in San Francisco, California. He was educated in the schools in
                    Missouri where he graduated from Central College in 1941, and from the
                    Washington University Medic al School in 1944. Most of his training in pathology
                    was obtained at Washington University under Robert A. Moore. In 1946 and 1947 he
                    served as Chief of Pathology, Command Laboratory, European Command, in Darmstadt
                    and Heidelberg. During this time he was detailed for a short period of special
                    duty in Vienna, where he had the opportunity to observe the teaching methods and
                    instruction in pathology and other fields at the Allgemeines Krankenhaus.
                    Although his principal interests and activities have been in the field of
                    general pathology, Dr. SMith has maintained a special interest in
                    neuropathology. He had short periods of special experience in the latter field
                    at Montefiore Hospital in New York and at the Mayo Clinic, and served as
                    neuropathologist for the Washington University group from 1948 to 1955. He is
                    the author of the chapter relative to that speciality in 'Surgical
                    Pathology' by Dr. L. V. Ackerman, with whom Dr. Smith was associated in teh
                    Department of Surgical Pathology at Barnes Hospital. Dr. Smith's
                    investigative interests have concentrated particularly on quantitative
                    histochemical studies in brain tissue, and in certain experimental
                    investigations in long term iron term overload and its effect on the systematic
                    storage of iron. In addition, he has participated in various studies relative to
                    speical aspects, chiefly morphological, of topics in general pathology and
                    neuropathology.... Dr. Smith is a member of the Council of the International
                    Academy of Pathology, the American Association of Pathologists and
                    Bacteriologists, the American Society of Clinical Pathologists, the Virginia
                    Society for Pathology, the Medical Society for Virginia and the American Medical
                    Association, and is an associate member of the American Academy of Neurology. He
                    is also a member of Alpha Omega Alpha and Sigma Xi. Dr. Smith is married and has
                    three children, the youngest of whom is a native Virginian." </abstract>
   <physicalDescription>
      <form authority="aat">black-and-white photographs</form>
      <digitalOrigin>reformatted digital</digitalOrigin>
      <internetMediaType>image/tiff</internetMediaType>
      <note displayLabel="Staff Note">Original Negative Present</note>
      <note displayLabel="Copy Negative"/>
   </physicalDescription>
   <note type="admin">Negative included in folder</note>
   <subject authority="tgn">
      <hierarchicalGeographic>
         <country>United States</country>
         <state>Virginia</state>
         <city>Charlottesville</city>
      </hierarchicalGeographic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
      <topic>Faculty</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
      <topic>Students</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject authority="lcsh">
      <name type="corporate" authority="naf">
         <namePart>University of Virginia</namePart>
      </name>
      <topic>Health System</topic>
   </subject>
   <relatedItem type="series" displayLabel="Part of">
      <titleInfo>
         <nonSort>The</nonSort>
         <title>University of Virginia Visual History Collection</title>
      </titleInfo>
   </relatedItem>
   <relatedItem type="series" displayLabel="Appears in">
      <titleInfo>
         <title>Uva Medical Alumni News Letter</title>
      </titleInfo>
      <part>
         <detail type="volume">
            <number>July-August 1958</number>
         </detail>
         <detail type="issue">
            <number/>
         </detail>
      </part>
   </relatedItem>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordContentSource authority="marcorg">viu</recordContentSource>
      <recordOrigin>Created programmatically by Digital Curation Services.</recordOrigin>
      <languageOfCataloging>
         <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
      </languageOfCataloging>
      <recordCreationDate encoding="w3cdtf">2012-08-15T19:06:29.731Z</recordCreationDate>
   </recordInfo>
</mods>